<xml>
<head>
<title>Signals and Slots</title>
</head>
<body>

<p>Signals and slots are used for communication between objects. In GUI programming we often
want a change in one component to be notified to another component. More generally, we want objects
of any kind to be able to communicate with one another. In ClanLib we started using signals
in ClanGUI, but broadened it up into other areas, like network and input.</p>

<p>Older toolkits achieve this kind of communication using callbacks. A callback is a pointer to a
function, so if you want a processing function to notify you about some event you pass a pointer
to another function (the callback) to the processing function. The processing function then calls
the callback when appropriate. Callbacks have two fundamental flaws. Firstly they are not type safe.
We can never be certain that the processing function will call the callback with the correct arguments.
Secondly the callback is strongly coupled to the processing function since the processing function must
know which callback to call.</p>

<p>In ClanLib we have an alternative to the callback technique. We use signals and slots. A signal is
emitted when a particular event occurs. ClanLib's components have many pre-defined signals. To handle
the signals that you are interested in, you connect the signal to a slot.</p>

<p>Signals are emitted by objects when they change their state in a way that may be interesting to
the outside world. This is all the object does to communicate. It does not know or care whether
anything is receiving the signals it emits. This is true information encapsulation. A signal can be
connected to as many slots as you desire.</p>

<p>A list box, for example, emits both highlighted() and activated() signals. Most objects will probably only be
interested in activated() but some may want to know about which item in the list box is currently highlighted.
If the signal is interesting to two different objects you just connect the signal to slots in both objects.</p>

<p>When a signal is emitted, the slots connected to it are executed immediately, just like a normal function
call. The emit will return when all slots have returned.</p>

<p>Slots can be used for receiving signals, but they are normal member functions. A slot does not
know if it has any signals connected to it.</p>

<p>Slot objects maintains connection state to the signals to which they are connected. When a slot
object is destroyed, the signals to which it was connected will be automatically informed,
and subsequently disconnected. However, this also means that it's important to be aware that 
you have to store the slots somewhere (even though they slots themselves are never used actively).</p>

<p>A minimal C++ class declaration might read:</p>
<code>
	class Foo
	{
	public:
		Foo();
		int get_value() const { return val; }
		void set_value(int);

	private:
		int val;
	};
</code>

<p>Adding a signal to this:</p>

<code>
	class Foo
	{
	public:
		Foo();
		int get_value() const { return val; }
		void set_value(int);

		CL_Signal_v1<int> sig_value_changed;

	private:
		int val;
	};
</code>

<p>This class has the same internal state, and public methods to access the state, but in addition it has
support for component programming using signals and slots: this class can tell the outside world that
its state has changed by emitting a signal, sig_value_changed.</p>

<p>The template-type of the signal class is called CL_Signal_v1. The _v1 means void, 1 parameter. If we
wanted a type with 2 parameters, we would create a signal of type CL_Signal_v2:</p>
<code>
	CL_Signal_v2<int, const std::string &text> sig_another_example;
	CL_Signal_v3<char, char, int> sig_yet_another_example;
</code>
<p>Currently void is the only return type supported, so all signals are called CL_Signal_v?.</p>

<h3>Emitting signals</h3>
<p>Here is a possible implementation of Foo::set_value():</p>

<code>
	void Foo::set_value(int v)
	{
		if (v != val)
		{
			val = v;
			sig_value_changed(v);
		}
	}
</code>

<p>The line sig_value_changed(v) emits the signal sig_value_changed from the object. As you can see, you emit
a signal by calling the signal as a function(arguments). Examples on the _v2 and _v3 signals mentioned above:</p>
<code>
	sig_another_example(10, "Hello world");
	sig_yet_another_example('a', 'b', 10);
</code>

<h3>Connecting to signals</h3>

<p>Connecting to a signal is pretty straightforward as well:</p>
<code>
	class FooTester
	{
	public:
		FooTester();
		void test();

	private:
		void on_value_changed(int val);

		Foo foo;
		CL_Slot slot_value_changed;
	}
	
	FooTester::FooTester()
	{
		slot_value_changed = foo.sig_value_changed.connect(this, &FooTester::on_value_changed);
	}

	void FooTester::test()
	{
		foo.set_value(49);
	}

	void FooTester::on_value_changed(int val)
	{
		std::cout << "New value from foo object is " << val << std::endl;
	}
</code>

<p>Explanation:</p>
<code>
	CL_Slot slot_value_changed;
</code>
<p>Make sure you store the CL_Slot object somewhere, otherwise the slot is disconnected when it is destroyed
(goes out of scope for instance). Put it in your class definition or similar; just don't make it a local variable.</p>

<code>
	slot_value_changed = foo.sig_value_changed.connect(this, &FooTester::on_value_changed);
</code>
<p>Each signal has a connect() function, which returns a CL_Slot object you need to keep. It takes
two parameters; the object of the receiving slot, and the definition of the receiving slot. Most often the first
argument will be <b>this</b>, but you can actually connect it to another class than your current object:</p>
<code>
	slot_value_changed = foo.sig_value_changed.connect(myOtherObject, &OtherObject::on_value_changed);
</code>

<h3>Slot Container</h3>
<p>CL_SlotContainer is a utility class which can store CL_Slots for you. Its syntax is as follows:
<code>
	CL_SlotContainer slots;
      ...
      slots.connect(mySignal1, this, &MyApp::on_signal1);
      slots.connect(mySignal2, this, &MyApp::on_signal2);
      slots.connect(mySignal3, this, &MyApp::on_signal3);
</code>
<p>You see the syntax for connecting signals using a CL_SlotContainer is a little bit different than the
CL_Slot method (example below).</p>
<code>
	CL_Slot slot1, slot2, slot3;
      ...
	slot1 = mySignal1.connect(this, &MyApp::on_signal1);
	slot2 = mySignal2.connect(this, &MyApp::on_signal2);
	slot3 = mySignal3.connect(this, &MyApp::on_signal3);
</code>

<h3>Disconnecting slots</h3>

<p>It is possible to disconnect a slot from its signal. This is automatically done when the slot
is deleted/leaves scope, but you can also call the signal.disconnect() function to disable a slot.</p>

<code>
	CL_Slot slot1;
	slot1 = mySignal1.connect(this, &MyApp::on_signal1);

	...

	mySignal1.disconnect(slot1);
</code>

<h3>Virtual slots</h3>

<p>ClanLib supports "virtual" slots, meaning you can override previously connected slots.
This works like the inheritage in C++, you can call earlier hooked up signals from the
overridden slot.</p>

<p>A normal connect looks like this:</p>

<code>
CL_Slot slot = window.sig_close().connect(this, &App::on_close);

void App::on_close() { ... }

</code>

<p>But to override any previously connected signals, you use the connect_virtual method:</p>

<code>
CL_Slot slot = window.sig_close().connect_virtual(this, &App::on_close);

void App::on_close(CL_SlotParent_v0 &super)
{
	if(I_want_to_call_parent_slow)
		super();
}

</code>

<p>Note that the connected function must have an extra parameter, the CL_SlotParent.
This is a reference to the previously connected signal, and you can call it if
you want, just like virtual methods in C++.</p>

<h3>Userdata</h3>

<p>When a signal is fired, the connected slots are called with the parameters defined in the signal.
Sometimes you want to add extra information to each slot, and for that ClanLib provides userdata.
It is used by adding an extra variable when connecting to the signal.</p>

<code>
	void App::on_signal(int a, int b)
	{
	}

	CL_Signal_v2<int, int> mySignal;

	CL_Slot slot = mySignal.connect(this, &App::on_signal);
</code>

<p>This is how you would connect to a normal signal, without using any userdata. The signal
requires two params, and you supply a function with two params.</p>

<code>
	void App::on_signal(int a, int b, std::string userdata)
	{
	}

	CL_Signal_v2<int, int> mySignal;

	std::string text = "Hello";

	CL_Slot slot = mySignal.connect(this, &App::on_signal, text);
</code>	

<p>Here we used the exact same signal, but added a string parameters as a userdata. Each 
time the signal is now fired, the userdata string will contain the string "hello".</p>

<p>You can use any type for the userdata, be it string, ints, whatever.</p>

<code>
	CL_SlotContainer slots;
	slots.connect(button1.sig_button_press(), this, &App::on_button_press, 1);
	slots.connect(button2.sig_button_press(), this, &App::on_button_press, 2);
	slots.connect(button3.sig_button_press(), this, &App::on_button_press, 3);
</code>

<p>In this example, userdata is used to connect several button clicks to the same function,
but with an extra userdata integer describing which button was pressed.</p>

<h3>Specific ClanLib signals</h3>

<p>All signals in ClanLib is a little bit different than explained in this overview so far - they are all functions.
The only effect this has on your code is that you put parenthesis behind the signal when connecting to it.
Some examples:</p>

<code>
CL_Mouse: (clanDisplay)
	static CL_Signal_v2<int, int> &sig_move();
	static CL_Signal_v1<const CL_InputEvent &> &sig_button_press();
	static CL_Signal_v1<const CL_InputEvent &> &sig_button_release();

CL_Component: (clanGUI)
	CL_Signal_v1<const CL_InputEvent &> & sig_mouse_down();

CL_Button: (clanGUI)
	CL_Signal_v1<bool> &sig_toggled();
	CL_Signal_v0 &sig_clicked();

Usage examples:
	CL_Slot slot1 = CL_Mouse::sig_move().connect(this, &App::on_mouse_move);
	CL_Slot slot2 = button->sig_clicked().connect(this, &GUIApp::on_button_clicked);
	CL_Slot slot3 = component->sig_mouse_down().connect(this, &GUIApp::on_component_mouse_down);

	void App::on_mouse_move(int x, int y);
	void GUIApp::on_button_toggled(bool state);
	void GUIApp::on_component_mouse_down(const CL_InputEvent &key);
</code>

<p>As you see, the only different is the parenthesis - sig_clicked() instead of sig_clicked.</p>

<h3>More examples</h3>

<p>If you need to see some real world examples of signals and slots, have a look at the <a href="gui_overview.html">GUI overview</a>.</p>

<p>Thanks to TrollTech and their QT toolkit for their Signal & Slot explanation; this overview was 
based on theirs.</p>

</body>
</xml>